[SPEAKER_00]: So, recently there was a question about ignorance and how can we uproot ignorance, how can we notice it, you know, during the day and uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one of the manifestations of ignorance is distracting ourselves, acts of distraction, turning away from what you feel, turning away from unpleasant things, just trying to go into this oblivious state of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it's pleasant as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just kind of... Well, it's not even specifically pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, just seemingly offers you a break from pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the pleasure of that indolence is simply determined by how much pressure you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But often, it's not even pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So people find themselves in a bored state, but then they can't help and just sort of do this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have no pleasure from it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still have to distract yourself from it, from other things that are pressuring you unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason you distract yourself is because it gives you a release from the pressure that you are... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...generally feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But much like sensuality, it's the same principle, because the release you get from distraction is the release that you get through senses, which is what pressures you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: The senses pressure you, and the only way for you to have a release from that pressure is to give in to the senses more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, nothing changes on the level of senses, which is why you're pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that changes, then, is the amount of you actively ignoring the reality of your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things that are distraction... things themselves are not a distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your attitude that finds distraction in doing certain things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, sometimes those things are very different, depending on people.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not always the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, so you... you try to distract yourself from pain...
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not specifically...
[SPEAKER_01]: But through sensuality, so you can actually... Well, that's why... that's why the distraction always leads to further sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are cultivating the basis of that indolence, you're cultivating the value of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all within the central being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's all pertaining to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you find a way to relieve yourself of the pressure of the senses without engaging with the senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without... and when I say engaging, that's usually what people kind of do to distract themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either find meaningless tasks or even meaningful tasks.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's tasks that have a reason for performing, but you do it for the real reasons of just distracting yourself from yourself, which is too unpleasant, too much of a burden, too much of a pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, commonly, people will distract themselves by just, you know, I'm not seeking sensuality specifically, but I'll go out and hang out with friends, just to kill some time, watching movies, entertainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing like extra sensual, but in itself it's still visual sort of distraction, audible music.
[SPEAKER_01]: Music, you know, many people just constantly have music playing in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the silence becomes too pressuring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've had, like, you get tired from general working.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tired from work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you watch a... so, then you have to switch on a movie, listen to music and be a passive... Yeah, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you want to relax from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you're jaded from having to deal with sense input the whole day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're physically tired and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can simply relax by going to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you realize you have a choice there, and you choose to sit for another three hours of enduring the senses and watch a movie.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't really relax you, because it's not... it hasn't taken you away from the senses, like when you fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what has happened there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's just enabled your mind to go into a state of self-ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, watching a movie is not in itself immoral or not virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you do it for the complete reasons, basically, of just self-ignoring, ignoring the state that you are in, that you find then relaxing, that's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's your reason behind unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're tired from your senses, go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not go back to the senses and find something that will just put you in a state of oblivion, while you're still pressured by the same senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's something more dangerous with that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's... Well, it's dangerous because you realize that only true non-pressure relief of that burden is when you're not dependent on the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you are cultivating the state of ignoring as your form of relief that you know and value, that's very much dependent on the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that which is the only relief you know, it's not a relief at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's making things worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, I mean, you then inevitably drift more and more into valuing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you had, again, you had a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You couldn't have just went to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you also have an option to, you know, have visual stimulation that will make you forget about yourself for an hour and a half.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the problem is being pressured by the senses, why is your form of relief forgetting about yourself, which has nothing to do with the senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that your relief?
[SPEAKER_01]: Surely, if senses are the ones that are pressuring you, your relief should be have a break from the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you kind of know it's senses that are pressuring you, yet then the relief that you have, that you value, that you cultivate, is the relief of ignoring yourself in regard to your senses and don't do anything about the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the senses are the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it not just puts you more into sensuality, but it basically makes you develop even more distorted views of where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you start valuing that state of self-ignoring, of unawareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you're not distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why delusion is the hardest to see and hardest to uproot, the stickiest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because you value that, oh, I just deserve to have a break.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, go and sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but I want to watch a movie.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your break means engagement with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only result of that is no change in the level of senses, how much you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result is how much you're unaware of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're cultivating
[SPEAKER_01]: A habit of unawareness in regard to yourself, in regard to your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even as I said, even when you're not necessarily distracting yourself, that is your view now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You value unawareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any opportunity you get, you will be unaware.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're narrowing down the recognition of your own situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so dangerous and that's why both ill-will and sensuality are rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That attitude of delusion...
[SPEAKER_00]: Helps me forget my situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by forgetting your situation, you then... you cultivate then that kind of basis of forgetfulness in regard to other things that you shouldn't be forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as motivation for your actions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that... building up that kind of habit, you are... the state of your mind that you're developing is this
[SPEAKER_00]: Inactive mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is complete, yeah, dull, opaque, obtuse, indolent, inactive, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is absolutely no, no recognition of thinking going on there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no right thinking going on there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing that, wait, why, if senses are the one that are making me tired, why do I hold a view that state of unawareness is my relaxation?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize there's no reason for that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you hold it is because you never thought about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you do start reflecting upon it and abandon that view, then you realize that absolute, 100% alertness throughout the day cannot make you tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has nothing to do with your tiredness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, there is never an excuse then to be unmindful and unaware.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You spend the whole day practicing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not tiring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why he said you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have too much of pondering, too little pondering, too slack, too tight, but you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not tiring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mindfulness... Mindfulness and awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, awareness is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is then awareness felt like you're... it's tiring you, it's work?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't understood it, you're not doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not doing it rightly, because you keep cultivating, then, the attitude that the non-work and relaxation is unawareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no reason for that attitude, except your own habit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just... just present moment, whatever here and now, don't think about tomorrow, don't think about what happened yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just hear what you have, just really be with the music.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's how mindfulness is, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be with the movie, be with the... Be with the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experience now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is recollectiveness of yesterday and what's in store for you tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the same time, presently, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not exclusion of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha would say, even when you go to bed, you go bed mindfully with the thought when you wake up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you truly switch off from the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you wake up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment you wake up, you don't need time to pick up your awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your awareness is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can cultivate that if you don't willingly and consciously choose to go the paths of unawareness and distraction and indolence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indolence is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Laziness, dullness, indolence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Laziness of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, laziness of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: The work of understanding, say, what mindfulness is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the mind is lazy, mind won't be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind is lazy, mind won't have energy to make the effort and reflect upon things that need to be reflected upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind is lazy, it's not going to even self-interrogate in terms of your motivation stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just going to go along with the path of least resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the mind is lazy, those four right strivings are not present.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind is lazy, there are no factors of enlightenment being cultivated.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind values laziness and indolence and delusion of that kind, those four energies, four powers, are not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if the mind is not lazy, so it...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, initially, you might feel like, oh, if I practice not lazy, you feel all, like, wound up, because you're practicing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's because you don't know what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you work through that, you realize, actually, mindfulness is effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollectedness is effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how tired, how physically fatigued I am, bombarded by the unpleasant sort of enduring of heat, cold, work, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having mind resting has nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my own assumption of this is what rest is, completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: While in reality then,
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that results into is unawareness, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no actual factual, because even after you watch a movie, you have to go and sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you're really tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never really rested, yet you have to go through these motions of what you deem restfulness, so to speak, is, which is centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only known escape from pain is through seeking pleasure of centrality, and this is like a low-key type of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no benefit there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So distracting yourself...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely non-beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...being passive to images on the screen or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you try to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you try to present, oh, it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a documentary or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but is that the real motivation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a necessity for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the motivation for watching it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need a break.
[SPEAKER_01]: Break from what?
[SPEAKER_01]: From the senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: By engaging more with the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having a mind which is active or alert, an alert mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's somehow... obviously, if you don't have an alert mind, it's quite painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite... it's a lot of work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot of... Yeah, well, that... compared to... basically, you're already in a state of being dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't practice mindfulness, you're as if dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it's almost coming back to... Yeah, you're fully... coming to life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, coming to life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escaping death by practicing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what the illusion is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those little things you give in... you give in to throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I work hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you did.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need a break.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: How you go about it, that's your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you need a break by just sitting quietly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to sleep?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you need a break by entertaining yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: With what?
[SPEAKER_01]: With the senses that made you tired in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of making the mind strong, making the mind alert, fully active, aware, constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts, virtues, the first thing, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to understand correctly what that effortless mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're doing mindfulness with effort, it's not the mindfulness you should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, it's not the mindfulness that needs to be cultivated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not going to start perfectly right off the bat, but if you know that you need to find the mindfulness that is effortless, that doesn't depend on the senses and what you attend to and so on, then you will be seeking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, trial and error, you can arrive at it eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you are tired, burdened, you know, physically tired, physically burdened, enduring elements, none of that would be mentally tiring, because none of that is mentally tiring.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make it mentally tiring by wanting to practice an awareness of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say, one is contemplating dhamma, one is thinking about an aspect, but it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of... you have to put effort in your thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to put some energy there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... that's not effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have... you can't expect that type of thinking or figuring... investigation to happen effortlessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll watch my breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then contemplation will magically occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to understand... Oh, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, all those notions that... that many people would have of such practices would be dispelled if they were just to start reading suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, more systematically, just read the actual suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, on many occasions, the Buddha would say himself, like, there's that famous sutta, when he said, he said, oh, what if, what if I were to not think any unwholesome thought and only think, make effort to think wholesome thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he spent day and night just thinking right things and not thinking the bad things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, tireless energy arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He could think only what he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he was like, through work, built up that energy momentum.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when he purified his thinking, nothing unwholesome would be entertained, welcomed, maintained, encouraged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he says, okay, what if I were to now calm myself down?
[SPEAKER_01]: But not by not thinking or not paying attention to whatever I think it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply, how do I take this step further?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking and pondering, that now you develop calmness on account of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through cancellation of your thoughts, but through basically rising up, finding what calmness is within the thinking mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But first, you need to develop the thinking mind correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, that's what I mean, like, that energy is a, it's, it's a must.
[SPEAKER_01]: Effort, repetition, drilling, training.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I said that probably before, but I remember when I started it in the suttas as a layman, and, you know, you have all these notions, and then the Buddha kept talking about the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: He trains himself thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the beginning, I remember, I couldn't quite, like, what is there to train?
[SPEAKER_01]: You either become enlightened, or you're not enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you might train indirectly, like you keep the precepts, you do the right things, but then enlightenment happens to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how do you train the enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_01]: It did not make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you read the suttas more and more and say, no, that's what enlightenment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rising above the unenlightening things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way you can rise above it is through manly effort, manly strength, manly determination, manly training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manly contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manly contemplation, manly perseverance, manly patience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever I was trying to talk about, the similes of the warrior and so on, it's not poetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's making an effort in investigation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like I'm blindly making effort in focusing on my nostrils.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's the result of that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the point?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom comes out of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Full understanding is what arahantship is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I understanding?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I making effort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: To understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, am I clearly thinking towards understanding?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then, I can know for safely, then, that I don't understand, but I will not understand for sure, if I don't at least try to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do I then go about trying to understand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that manifest, then, as practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: A lot of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not just read it, and then get inspired on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you know, might... will probably happen inevitably, but don't take that to be the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you're inspired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now go back to the same sutta that inspired you so much and understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said many times before, you will know if you're understanding the meaning of the dhamma that the Buddha laid out, if you're becoming incapable to suffer amidst suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not if you don't suffer at the moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the worst thing were to happen to you, how much would you suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Before you understood what you understood, and now after you understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Has that suffering diminished?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can have a sense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not... you will not know exactly how much has diminished, but you will have a sense that I am less touched by suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is less pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because I'm running away, justifying, psychologizing, trying to avoid it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply because, like, it cannot touch me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you become fearless as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who doesn't experience fear is not fearless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who, within, like, within the experience of fear, doesn't fear it, he's a fearless one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're constantly hiding or frightening, away from frightening things, you don't know if you're fearless or not, because you're just hiding from fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you know if you're fearless?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just fear-free at the time, but you're not fearless, as in incapable of being afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a completely different thing, that you can only develop through understanding and overcoming fear, existential fear, fear of restraint, fear of giving things up, fear of losing your possessions, your attachments, your loved ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Arahant, he's the fearless one, incapable of being afraid.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not brave.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bravery, you need the fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, just go against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on a practical level,
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be trying to understand the teachings of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the beginning, it's going to be hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, when you learn any... you're learning any new subject or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to read the suttas, practice virtue and precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greater your virtues are, basically, the greater potential for understanding you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you start reading the suttas, and you will.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start making effort to understand them,
[SPEAKER_01]: And keep reading, and your mind will get hooked onto different aspects that will make more sense, that you think about more through, and clarify them, then suddenly new aspects become revealed, then you go into them, then you go into them, and that should be your meditation as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, before I was enlightened, while I was still unenlightened bodhisattva, I decided, what if I were to think only wholesome thoughts, and not think unwholesome thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're a patujana,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even near the right view, far from arahantship, that is the only thing you should be doing, trying to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any meditation you do, concentration, relaxation practice, has nothing to do with the dhamma, because you have no dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, again, without the right view, there is no meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how can you meditate, if you don't know what meditation is?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean in the other talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: We covered it about meditation centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forgot the title.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's where you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you want this meditation, your meditation technique, they make you feel all right and peaceful and so on, is because you want pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want agreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But which means you're choosing to not do the work of getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you practically go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if sometimes thinking gets like... it's just too much, so to speak, yeah, okay, relax a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't start valuing that relaxation from work, because you haven't done the necessary work.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's all these things you can do, like, if you read a sutta and it says, you know, understand the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question, what is the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, all of that, all of that will become more apparent once you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking about the absolute beginner who comes to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start reading the suttas, you start getting a sense, and then you can have your own interrogations of the things that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to constantly
[SPEAKER_01]: Be kind of reinvigorated with the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, body, feeling, feeling, feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say feeling to myself or to somebody else, what am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we've done those interrogations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, someone might read the sutta about, okay, feeling this, feelings this, body that, and read the sutta, and then just stay at that level of
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, very nice, very nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, inspiration.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that other level of... that needs... there needs to be effort made.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does this mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the meaning here?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very unpleasant, especially if you're not trained in doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'd rather... And most people are not trained in doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd rather just read the sutta nicely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get a nice feeling from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with all these talks and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we try to make our talks
[SPEAKER_01]: As as kind of engaging as possible, but I'm sure many people would just be inspired by it and, you know, inspired by the energy we put out or whatever, I don't know, and not actually... All the style.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the style, the way we speak, I don't know, but be that as it may, you need to understand what's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're just running off on an inspiration, you're not doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's even worse, because you think you're doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, before, at least, you knew you were not doing the work, and you're not doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, you think you're doing the work simply by being inspired, by not making effort to understand, while you're not doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, it's going to be twice as hard to snap out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, by the pretext of doing work, you feel great, inspired.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma is so easy, or so inspiring.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, so are you free from suffering on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no understanding taking place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are you inspired about?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm inspired that it gives me a nice feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gives me a nice feeling, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm inspired with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's inevitable to experience that when you either read the suttas or listen to a dhamma talk by somebody.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either going to approve or disapprove on that level of your feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if that's your... that's as far as you go...
[SPEAKER_00]: Your criteria...
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's your sole criteria, you're missing out either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, by the way, when people disapprove what's being said, not because of what's being said, it's just how it's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you clearly don't make an effort to understand what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone might listen to this and say, why is this wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I think it's wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I tell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Explain why it's right?
[SPEAKER_01]: This ajan is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he's cool.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: But why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I don't like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know why.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important part.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I remember when I was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I would take up random books from the library, philosophy books and so on, of clearly things that would be regarded as wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I would read it to understand why it's wrong, not just to get off on the righteousness that this is wrong, this is ridiculously wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I need to see why it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, oh, it's wrong because I took it because somebody else that I believe in said so.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not Buddhist or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, they were like reading in the Veda and then he would mention all these other philosophers and they were wrong and so on, but he wouldn't dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I found some of those books and I was like, okay, so I need to see why this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to see for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't just accept that this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, consequently, things that you regard as right, you start putting in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the unpleasant bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, things that I thought of, you know, I understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but why?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is this right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is this right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it right because it's absolutely contradiction-free?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're doubting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you know it's right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are acting as if you know it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not coming... it's only partially coming across the right instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, suttas, talks, but if you never actually start digging things up on that level, internally, making that effort, all of this is meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the yonisamanasikāra part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going back to that origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Origin of your views with which you are listening to this teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to then start doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your perspective consist of?
[SPEAKER_00]: Perspective, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it consist of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it based on?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it based upon?
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have this perspective on this, but on account of what I have such a perspective?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you realize, more often than not, in account of I'm finding it pleasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea of it, this, whatever, pleases me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I assume it is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I told you that, again, when I was a layman, I think probably my first year of reading the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was that
[SPEAKER_01]: In Digha Nikāi, I think, Samanyapāla Sutta, it was a sutta that lists about those six different wrongs.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was Samanyapāla.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was the fruits of the holy life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in that sutta, the Buddha describes these different, like, fundamental other different teachings, six different teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: About, you know, like, there is nobody getting killed, and then the simile of cutting the sword goes through the arm, and then there's nothing given.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determinism.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't know much about it at the time, and I was reading that sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a long sutta, so by the time I arrived at that bit, I was reading suttas before that, so by the time I arrived at that sutta,
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't read the leading-up sentence when the Buddha started celebrating on this view that said, these are the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: I kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So I just started reading these suttas and I thought the Buddha was teaching that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, there is nobody killed, because anatta, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the next one, like the... what was the other one that... that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was that... yeah, determinism, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The boiler that will kind of run its course, when you deplete the bad karma in itself, by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I was like, yeah, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I was reading these views, I was accepting all of them, thinking the Buddha is saying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when he finished, he said, see, that's why these views are wrong, lead to peril.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was like, oh my goodness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I realized even the stuff that I thought I understood about the Buddha and the teaching of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't, because I just literally accepted six different wrong views as one, as the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fortunately, that concern, I took on as a challenge, to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as, oh, I must cover this up and never read this sutta again, and just focus on things I think I understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that determinism wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's just this huge weight of opaque... you have no idea where to start.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no idea why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I better start making effort to find out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it made sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody gets killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: All religions teach the same, just in a different way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Already enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is like, actually, no, the Buddha said this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I do...
[SPEAKER_01]: I had... and again, fortunately, I had enough faith, even at that initial stage, in the suttas and the Buddha, to accept that, which I clearly did not see as wrong, that it's wrong, but not stay at that level, it's wrong, it's wrong, it's wrong, but it's something that needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if by understanding, as you're saying earlier, understanding different wrong views, you can uproot those wrong views that you... Yeah, you're getting clearer to what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a different way of progressing, but equally valid, or something you can do both, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all the views you have, as a praducian, are wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by undoing them, means by understanding them, you can arrive at the right one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not optional to go through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just some people need to do more of that, some people need to do less of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the work needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have, yeah, you have wrong views, but you don't even know what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know what...
[SPEAKER_01]: And even, you know, we have the examples in the suttas of people practicing out of faith, you know, the faith type, sadhana, sadhana, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people often, oh, I'll just focus on devotion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not what faith is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith is that, accepting that the Buddha is right, even if you have no factual proof for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that faith is relevant and valid only if now, on account of that faith, you start doing the same effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody can't do that just on account of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: He needs to start making more effort to even arrive at the point to do the effort on account of what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people just hear what the Buddha said and they'll do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, you need to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But these days, when you say faith, I'm a faith type and so on, just means basically bhakti yoga and your devotional worship.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there's nothing to do with faith that Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith in a doctor, faith in following a doctor prescription without comparing it to other doctors and so on, which some people need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, the work needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That effort needs to be made.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whichever type you are,
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You spoke about it a long time ago, about that mental relaxation again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you must watch out for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never want to give in to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mental indolence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just put my feet up for five minutes and not think about anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Find another way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's unawareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something you give in to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, I'm physically tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to think anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm physically tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've been walking 30 kilometers.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to sit down, put this bag down.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You sit down, put the bag down, even go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's where that ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choosing, on account of that, to give to unawareness, that's a completely unrelated thing, for which you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where delusion, same as with desire and so on, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on the maras domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on how tired you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not on the elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you getting, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: Relaxed, in terms of stopping what you're doing, they were tiring you, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you getting relaxed, or taking that relaxation then on the level of becoming unaware in your mind, because you worked so hard, that's not fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That bit is not fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like you overly welcoming it now, and put... and doing it on the level where it shouldn't be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean you must now contemplate dhamma furiously.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do that either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you mustn't give to unawareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... sometimes it's, you know, it's even in the sutras Buddha said, yeah, you might be making too much effort to figure things out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you drop the effort to figure things out, but it doesn't mean you drop your awareness of your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, alertness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But being in the present moment is effortless, because whether you want it or not, you're in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognition of the world of bodies, it's not a matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already have that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you seated now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let me, let me...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll get back to you on that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's effortless, that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to be attending and re-attending and recollect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is stop distracting yourself from it by making choices on the kind of sensuality aversion and distraction and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the effortless mindfulness is not done by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The effortless mindfulness is basically created by you not distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not turning away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not turning away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not consciously going into oblivion, oblivious state of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why greed, aversion, delusion and non-greed, non-aversion...
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, the Buddha said, he won't think.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't entertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will not welcome and sort of cherish.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that's rooted in non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, he will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tireless energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: No need to rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's it's tireless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nothing to do with that which tires you, which is the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But either way, it's going to be work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need to build it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to build it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like this fear to even just even begin a little bit, not even... Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's horrible.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, when... you're just bewildered.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you just have to... it's just... it's worse than the physical work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not incidental.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole humanity tends to turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Turn away from responsibility, from reason, turn away from rational thinking, recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Takes effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes enduring, it takes pain, it takes some greater reason to make you go into that direction of more resistance against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most people won't do that.